The Life Of Muhammadﷺ, The Makkan period by Imam Anwar Al-Awlaki.
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
Yesterday we talked about the importance of studying Seerah(سيرة).
And now we'll start with the first session on Seerah(سيرة), itself.
Now usually the authors or the scholars, who write about the life of Muhammadﷺ,
they do not usually start talking about his birth.
They would go a little bit before that,
actually about few thousand years before that
and they would talk about his father Ibrahim عليه السلام.
That's usually where they would start talking about Rasool Allah ﷺ,
they would talk about his ancestry, starting by Ibrahim عليه السلام.
The emphasis is on the Hajar(هاجر) and Ismail(اسماعيل) side of the story rather than the, Is'haaq(اسحاق) and Sarah(ساره),
because that's the lineage of Muhammadﷺ.
So, they would start by talking about the story of Ibrahim علبه السلام, Hajar(هاجر) and Sarah(ساره),
when they traveled to Hijaz(حجاز).
Ibrahim عليه السلام, his wife and his newborn son, traveled into Arabia, into the land of Hijaz(حجاز).
And Ibrahim(ابراهيم) took them to present day Makkah.
At that time, there was nothing there,
nobody was living there, there was no cultivation.
It was a dead Valley.
But the place where the House of Allah is built,
the place where the Al-Ka'aba(الكعبه) was built was sacred, since the world was created.
In fact, there's a difference of opinion on who is the first one to build Al-Ka'aba(الكعبه).
The majority opinion is that it was Ibrahim عليه السلام
but there are some scholars, who say that Adam(آدم) was the first one to build it.
Now, regardless of whether Ibrahimعليه السلام or Adamعليه السلام built it,
the place itself, whether there was a building on it or not, was holy and sacred from day one.
Ibrahim عليه السلام and his wife and son, arrived to the valley and in the place where Zam-Zam(زمزم) is currently,
obviously there wasn't Zam-Zam(زمزم) at that time.
Ibrahim عليه السلام left his wife and son, Ismael(اسماعيل).
He left with them some water and a leather bag of dates.
And he walked away.
He just turned away and left.
Now, Hajarعليها السّلام knew that Ya'ani(يعني) Ibrahimعليه السلام was gonna leave them
but she didn't expect to be left in such a place, in the middle of the desert.
So, she followed him and she said:
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم)! Are you gonna leave us in a place where there's no cultivation and there's no one living.?
Ibrahim عليه السلام did not answer back.
She asked him again, no response,
she asked him a third time, he didn't answer back,
and then Hajarعليها السّلام said:
آلَّهُ اَمَرَكَ بِهَذَا
Did Allah tell you to do so?.
Ibrahimعليه السلام said: Yes.
قَالَتْ فَلَنْ يُضَيِّعَنَ اِذَنْ
Then Allah will take care of us.
If this is a command from Allah, then I have trust in Allah that He will take care of us.
Look at the faith of this woman,
in the middle of nowhere.
But if this is the command of Allah, I have trusted in Allah, Allah will take care of us.
فَلَنْ يُضَيِّعَنَ الله
Allah will not waste us, Allah will not neglect us.
Ibrahim عليه السلام left and when he reached to a place where they cannot see him anymore.
Ibrahimعليه السلام turned around and faced Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) or the place of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
And he made Dua(دُعَا) to Allah.
He said:
رَبَّنَا إِنِّي أَسْكَنْتُ مِنْ ذُرِّيَّتِي بِوَادٍ غَيْرِ ذِي زَرْعٍ عِنْدَ بَيْتِكَ الْمُحَرَّمِ
رَبَّنَا لِيُقِيمُوا الصَّلَاةَ فَاجْعَلْ أَفْئِدَةً مِنَ النَّاسِ تَهْوِي إِلَيْهِمْ
وَارْزُقْهُمْ مِنَ الثَّمَرَاتِ لَعَلَّهُمْ يَشْكُرُونَ۝
Ibrahimعليه السلام said: O Allah, I'm leaving my offspring, in infertile land, a land where there is, no cultivation.
بِوَادٍ غَيْرِ ذِي زَرْعٍ
Next to your sacred house.
So, the place was known that it was sacred even though Al-Ka'aba(الكعبه) wasn't built.
And then Ibrahimعليه السلام made a Dua(دُعَا).
Now, you know the Maslow hierarchy of needs, the pyramid?
What is the foundation of the pyramid?
The bottom!
What is the first human need that needs to be satisfied?
What does it start with?
First thing is what?
Physiological needs, right?
That's the bottom of the pyramid.
So, that is the most important need for humans.
That's the base of the pyramid.
And then what's after that, what's the next step,
Psychological,
and then the third,
Social,
Physiological on the bottom,
Spiritual,
and then the peak is, Self-actualization.
So, that's the pyramid.
First of all, as a human being you want to satisfy the physiological necessary needs which are food and shelter.
After that, you want to have friends, have a social life, have a belonging, an Association.
So, those are the social needs,
and then you have the spiritual needs.
So, after you have achieved the physiological needs and the social needs
after that, you start thinking about religion, according to Maslow.
Finally, you have the self-actualization, which is on the top of the pyramid.
But according to Ibrahimعليه السّلام, the pyramid is inverted.
The first thing that he asked for was not food and drink or shelter.
The first thing he asked for, was:
رَبَّنَا لِيُقِيمُوا الصَّلَاةَ
The first thing that they asked for even though it would make sense that they would ask for...
I mean, we would assume that Ibrahimعليه السّلام, since he left them in a valley where there's, there's no cultivation,
the first thing he would ask for is to provide his family with food, for their survival.
But Ibrahimعليه السلام started in his Dua(دُعَا) by saying;
رَبَّنَا لِيُقِيمُوا الصَّلَاةَ
O Allah so that, they may establish prayer.
So, the first need that he asked for,
or the first thing that he mentioned, was spiritual needs, Salah(صلاة),
اِقَامَةِ الصَّلَاةْ
Establishing the prayers
and then he said:
فَاجْعَلْ أَفْئِدَةً مِنَ النَّاسِ تَهْوِي إِلَيْهِمْ
And then make or put their love, in hearts of people.
Ya'ani(يعني) make people love them.
So, he is asking Allahسبحانه وتعالى to draw people to his family,
and to make them love his family.
So, he's asking for the social needs,
and then finally he said:
وَارْزُقْهُمْ مِنَ الثَّمَرَاتِ
Then provide them with fruits.
So, Ibrahimعليه السلام is starting by asking for Salah(صلاة), spiritual needs
and then social needs and then physiological needs.
But even when he asked Allahسبحانه وتعالى to provide them with Samaraat(ثمرات), fruits,
he also connected it, to Ibadah(عبادة) and said:
لَعَلَّهُمْ يَشْكُرُونَ
So, that they may be grateful.
So, even when he was asking Allah to provide them with worldly things,
he was still connecting it to religion.
لَعَلَّهُمْ يَشْكُرُونَ
Give them fruit, so that they will be grateful to you.
And that is true self-actualization, when Allah becomes everything for you.
When you're eating, when you're drinking, when you're sleeping, you're doing everything for Allah.
That is the true tranquility and that is the self-actualization that neither did Maslow, or anybody else achieve,
except the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allah and Aouliyaa(أولياء) of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
And then Ibrahimعليه السّلام left.
Hajar(هَاجر) made use of the small amount of food that he left with them,
but obviously after a short while they ran out of food
and Hajarعليها السّلام was breastfeeding Ismail(اسماعيل)
and her milk was drying up, because she's thirsty and hungry.
And now Ismailعليه السّلام is beginning to cry, he's hungry.
So, Hajarعليها السّلام couldn't afford seeing her son, agonizing in pain.
So, she left him and she started climbing a hill.
A Hill, which was called later As-Saffa(ألصفاء).
She climbed on top of that hill to see, if she can see anybody in the horizon.
She would look left and right, and would see no one.
So, she would climb down the hill.
And when she would reach the valley, she would tuck up her clothes and run.
And then she would climb another Hill,
which was later called Al-Marwa(ألمروة).
And she would reach the top and look in the horizon, if she can see anybody.
And her son is twisting and turning in pain.
And Hajarعليها السّلام is running up and down, these hills and she did that seven times.
The seventh time, when she reached the top of the hill.
She heard a sound
and she was staring around to see where that sound is coming from.
And to her amazement, she saw that the sound was coming from beneath the feet of Ismailعليه السّلام.
Jibreelعليه السلام descended and was digging the well of Zam-Zam(زمزم).
And the water was coming out from beneath his feet.
Hajarعليها السلام was rushing in happiness to the source of the water.
And because it's a dry desert, and it would soak up, all of the water.
She was making a pool around the water to contain it.
Rasool Allah ﷺ when he was narrating the story, he said:
رَحِمَ اللهُ اُمُّ اِسْمَاعِيْلْ لَوْ تَرَكَتْهَا لَكَانَتْ زَمْزَمْ عَيْنَنْ تَجْرِيْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
May Allah have mercy, on the mother of Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل),
if she would have left the water alone, it would have been a flowing river.
But because of her interference it was a well,
she was trying to contain the water and she didn't allow it to flow.
If she would have left the miracle as it was going without interfering, it would have been a flowing stream.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ smiled and said: May Allah have mercy on her.
Hajarعليها السّلام, Think for a moment.
What were her feelings, when she was running up and down those hills?
Her heart must have been broken, she might have been crying
because of the pain and suffering of seeing her son die in front of her eyes.
Hajar(هَاجر) was a believing woman, she was a righteous woman,
and Allahسبحانه وتعالى was testing her,
and Allahسبحانه وتعالى was hiding for her something in the future that she didn't know.
So, at that time, naturally as a mother, she must have been in an extreme pain, seeing her son crying,
and she's in the middle of nowhere, running up and down these mountains.
Now, just imagine if Hajar(هَاجر) was resurrected at the time of Hajj(حج)
and she would have a chance to see, what Muslims from all over the world are doing.?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
When he was mentioning the story of Hajar(هَاجر) going up and down As-Saffa Wal Marwa(ألصفا والمروة),
And that is why.? We go between Al-Saffah(الصَّفا) and Marwa(مَروَاة).
So, we are following the footsteps of Hajarعليها السّلام.
We are going up and down As-Saffa Wal Marwa(ألصفا والمروة) to follow the footsteps of our mother Hajarعليها السّلام.
if Hajar(هَاجر) knew that the time will come, when people will come from the four corners of the world,
to follow her footsteps in millions, to do what she did.
She would have went through As-Saffa Wal Marwa(ألصفا والمروة) with, the big smile on her face.
So, dear brothers and sisters, as a Muslim, as a believer when you are going through these trials,
you might have a certain mindset, you might have a certain feeling,
but you don't know what's waiting for you on the other side.
You don't know what Allah is hiding for you in the future.
This is the gift, this is the present,
that Allahسبحانه وتعالى has given Hajar(هَاجر) in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
Just think about what Allahسبحانه وتعالى will give her in Aakhirah(آخِرَة).
So, when we go through some difficult situations, when Allahسبحانه وتعالى puts us through trials and tribulations,
let's always remember this,
let's remember that Hajar(هَاجر) went through this, and Allahسبحانه وتعالى provided her with something better,
that Allahسبحانه وتعالى was hiding something for her.
Musaعليه السلام when he was with his family.
When he was lost in the desert, it was a cold windy night,
and Musaعليه السلام lost his way, he didn't know what direction was Egypt?
And he saw a fire in the distance.
So, he told his wife, I will go to that fire, so that I can bring you with light and guidance.
He wants to bring light because it was a dark night,
and he wanted to have some warmth in the cold weather,
and he wanted guidance.
He expected since there's a fire in the desert, there must be some people there.
It's a bonfire and there's some people around it.
So, I'll go and ask them for directions.
That's all Musa(موسى) wanted.
He wanted some light for that dark night and he wanted guidance to Egypt.
But Allahسبحانه وتعالى was hiding something better for him.
Allahسبحانه وتعالى tells us the story in Qur'an.
When Musa عليه السلام went there, he met Allah and Allah spoke to him.
And rather than Musa(موسى), going back with light for that dark night and guidance to Egypt,
he came back with light for humanity.
And he came back with guidance,
not to Egypt, but to Jannah(جنة).
He went there and that was the announcement of his Prophet Hood.
It was done right then and there.
Musa عليه السلام lost in the desert went to the fire, Allahسبحانه وتعالى told him:
إِنَّنِي أَنَا اللَّهُ لَا إِلَٰهَ إِلَّا أَنَا فَاعْبُدْنِي وَأَقِمِ الصَّلَاةَ لِذِكْرِي
I am Allah there's no God besides me.
فَاعْبُدْنِي وَأَقِمِ الصَّلَاةَ لِذِكْرِي
Worship Me and established prayer, in My name.
Musaعليه السلام wanted something but he got something better.
The Sahabahرضي الله عنهم, they would go through difficulties, but Allah reserved for them the top levels of Jannah(جنة).
So, let's think about this, When we ourselves, go through moments of difficulty.
Now, in the desert, whenever you have a source of water,
it would immediately attract forms of life.
So, now birds were beginning to hover, over the well.
Because nothing was living there, it was a Death Valley.
There was a tribe called Jurhum(جرهم).
Who were nomads in that particular area?
And where did Jurhum(جرهم) come from?
Jurhum(جرهم) was a tribe that moved out of Yemen,
Yemen was the birthplace of the Arab people and the Arabic language.
And that is where the Arab tribes immigrated from.
And there were many mass immigrations, or waves of immigration that happened from Yemen in different times,
one of them, when the dam was destroyed and there's a whole chapter in Qur'an called Sabaa(سبا).
Which was the name of that kingdom.
Allah tells us the story that these were people, who built the first dam in the world.
And because of that dam, they had a year-round source of water.
So, even though you don't have a lot of rain in Arabia, the precipitation level is low.
But because of this dam, they had a year-round source of water.
And they had a massive network of irrigation.
That went for hundreds of miles.
So, suddenly, you have this semi-arid area, holding a huge population, because of the existence of water.
And there are some stories, there might be exaggeration, but it says that a woman would go out of her house
and go for a walk, with the basket on her head, and she would come back home and the basket is filled with fruits,
the fruits are just dropping from the trees.
But it does say in Qur'an that because of their wealth, and the cultivation that they had,
they didn't feel any pain in traveling.
Because it was a continuous series of colonies,
wherever they would go, there would be villages and towns and there was so much wealth,
so they did not feel the suffering and the difficulty of traveling, like the rest of the people of the world would.
So, these people because of their arrogance and disbelieve in Allah.
They said: We want to feel pain of traveling like everybody else.
So, they asked Allah, O Allah make it difficult on us, like everybody else.
And Allah did make it difficult on them and they rejected the message of Allah, so Allah destroyed the dam.
The dam was destroyed, and it flooded the area, and suddenly all of their agriculture collapsed.
So, you had the huge wave of immigration, which spread the Arab people out of Yemen into Al-Najad(ألنجد)
and Hijaz(حجاز) and Iraq(عراق) and Ash-Sham(ألشام).
So, you had some tribes settling in Oman(عمان).
Some of them settled in Najd(نجد), some of them settled in Hijaaz(حجاز).
Al-Aos Wal Khazraj(ألأوس والخزرج) settled in Madina,
and then you have a few of the Arab tribes, went to Syria, and some of them went into Iraq.
So, that is how the Arab people spread out of their small locality in Yemen.
I'm giving you this background history because Jurhum(جرهم) was one of these tribes.
However, Jurhum(جرهم) might have immigrated from Yemen before the dam Allah ho Alam(الله اعلم).
But anyway, they are one of the tribes that ended up moving out of Yemen and they went into Hijaz(حجاز).
They were familiar with the area around Makkah, they knew that, there was no water in that area.
So, when they saw birds hovering in the sky,
they wondered, what was going on in that particular area.?
So, they sent one or two people to go and investigate the matter.
So, these two men went and they came back and reported to their clan and told them that there is a well in that area.
So, now Jurhum(جرهم), they go to the place where Zam-Zam(زمزم) is located.
And they ask Hajar(هَاجر), a strange question and they get a stranger answer.
They told Hajar(هَاجر) can we settle in this place?
Now, the reason why this question is strange is, because this is a tribe of warriors.
And here they are getting permission from a lonely woman with her child.
I mean, if they want, they could have just pushed her away.
But they were very kind to ask her permission to stay there.
Even though it was an empty place, there was nobody living there, to start with.
And her answer was more amazing because she started to bargain and negotiate with them.
I mean, here you have a woman, who was alone with no power and no strength, no weapons, no army to help her
and she's negotiating and bargaining with them
and telling them well if you want to stay, I have a condition and that is the water belongs to us.
You can stay here but the water is mine.
The well belongs to me, they agreed.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
وَاَلْفَاهَا تُحِبُّ الْاُنْسْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ says; Deep in her heart, she wanted them to stay from the beginning
because she wanted to have some company.
But she was just negotiating with them to get a better deal.
And she did, and they ended up settling in that area, which later became known as Makkah.
Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) grew up with them and he adopted their language, he learned their language which was.?
What was their language.? Arabic.
Because Ibrahimعليه السلام his language was.?
What was the language of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم).?
Aramac from Iraq(عراق).
Ibrahimعليه السلام was from Iraq.
And they used to speak a different language in Iraq at that time.
So, Ismailعليه السلام was brought up by this Arab tribe and he adopted their language.
And he married a woman from among them.
So, this is the beginning of the lineage of Rasool Allah ﷺ, through Ismailعليه السلام  in Makkah.
Now, Jurhum(جرهم) had the political leadership in Makkah.
Later on, Ismailعليه السلام grew up and his father came and they built Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
The religious leadership in Makkah was with Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) and it continued down along the line of his descendants.
So, Jurhum(جرهم) never had the religious authority over Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
It was always in the hands of the descendants of Ismailعليه السلام.
But the political leadership was with Jurhum(جرهم).
Jurhum(جرهم), stayed in Makkah for a very long time, 2000 years.
They became corrupt, tyrannical,
so Allahسبحانه وتعالى sent on them, Khuza'a(خزاعه),
and Khuza'a(خزاعه) kicked them out of Makkah
This(خزاعه) is another tribe that came out from Yemen and then they settled in Hijaz(حجاز).
They went in and invaded Makkah and they kicked Jurhum(جرهم) out.
Jurhum(جرهم) before they left, they did two things.
Number 1:  they dumped the well of Zam-Zam(زمزم).
They filled it up and they erased all of its marks.
Number 2: And they stole the treasures which were inside Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
Khuza'a(خزاعه) now, became the new leaders of Makkah.
While the descendants of Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل), by that time, have already increased in numbers
and branched out and spread all over Arabia.
But there was one branch that remained in Makkah and that branch was?
Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
So, Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), is one of many different tribes who descended from Ismailعليه السلام,
they are called the descendants of Adnan(عدنان).
So, Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) were still living in Makkah, but now Makkah was ruled by Khuza'a(خزاعه).
The leader of Khuza'a(خزاعه), one of their leaders,
his name is Amr Bil Lohae Al-Khuzae(عمرو بن لوحي ألخزاعي).
And we're going to talk about his story later on, when we touch upon the religious background of Arabia.
But now we want to stick to the lineage of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
The head of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), Qusae Bin Kulaab(قصئ بن كلاب),
he was able to unify Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) and to lead a revolt against Khuza'a(خزاعه).
And he was able to drive them out completely from Makkah.
So, now finally, a descendant of Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل), combined the political and religious leadership of Makkah.
Not only that, but Qusae Bin Kulaab(قصئ بن كلاب) he consolidated all of the authorities,
or all of the different aspects of power in his hands.
He controlled Al-Hijabah(ألحجابه), which was the guardianship of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه), which was a very noble thing.
So, he was the guardian of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
He controlled Siqaya(سقايه) and Rifadah(رفادة),
which is the provision of water and food to the pilgrims.
Now to you, this might not seem as a big deal, I mean, so what if he was providing food and drink to the pilgrims,
but to them, this was considered to be such a great honor,
that you are the one, providing for the guests of Allah.
So, they used to fight on this.
So, what this responsibility entailed is that all of the Arabs, who would come for pilgrimage
would be hosted by the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
They would provide them with food throughout their stay in the season of Hajj(حَجْ).
So, Qusae Bin Kulaab(قصئ بن كلاب) also was responsible for that.
He also had control over a An-Nadwa(ألندوة),
An-Nadwa(ألندوة) was the assembly of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
It was like their parliament, he held control over that.
And he also held control over Al-Luwa'a(ألُّوَّاء), Al-Luwa'a(ألُّوَّاء) is banner of war.
In other words, he was the one, who had the power to declare war.
So, these were the authorities that Qusae Bin Kulaab(قصئ بن كلاب) had,
basically, he had every authority that existed in Makkah.
So, he was the absolute ruler of Makkah.
Qusae Bin Kulaab(قصئ بن كلاب) when he died,
these different aspects of authority were split among his children.
Some of them were, with Abd Manaf(عبد مناف), and some of them were with his other brothers.
The grandson of Qusae(قصىء), his name is Amr(عمرو),
he ended up inheriting from his father, the provisions of Al-Hajjaj(ألحجاج), providing them with food and drink.
Amr(عمرو) did something new, in feeding of Al-Hajjaj(ألحجاج),
rather than providing them with soup.
You know, they would cook the meat in big containers, and then they would feed the people soup,
because that way, you could feed the larger number.
What Amr(عمرو) did is.?
He started crushing bread into the soup,
so he would mix bread with the soup,
which was an upgrade to their meals.
Now, they're rather than just having soup,
they're having soup with Bread.
Now, the process of crushing the bread,
in Arabic is Hashm(هشم).
When you crush, something is called Hashm(هشم).
So he was nickname Haashim(هاشم).
So, he was nicknamed this man, Amr(عمرو), they called him Haashim(هاشم).
And this was the great grandfather of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, he was named Haashim(هاشم) because of crushing bread.
That wasn't his real name, his real name was Amr(عمرو).
Haashim(هاشم) married from Al-Madina.
He got married from Al-Madina.
And then he went to Phalastine(فلسطين) to do business.
And he passed away in Gaza(غزة).
He died in Gaza(غزة), he died and was buried in Gaza(غزة).
His wife became pregnant and she gave birth to a child,
who was named Shaybah(شيبه).
Shaybah(شيبه) means old man.
Now, why would anybody call a child a Shaybah(شيبه)?
The reason is he was born with some gray hair.
So, they named him, Shaybah(شيبه).
And because his father passed away, the mother stayed with her parents in Madina.
And he was brought up by his family in Madina.
One day a man comes into Madina, His name is Al-Muttalib(إلمطلب),
Al-Muttalib(إلمطلب) is Haashim(هاشم)'s brother.
He went into Madina, and he went to claim his nephew.
Because Haashim(هاشم)'s son, Shaybah(شيبه) was living where.?
In Madina.
So, his uncle Al-Muttalib(إلمطلب) came to claim him,
when he was eight years old, or something like that.
He said: We want to take him back to his land in Makkah.
The mother's side of the family refused to give him up.
But then Al-Muttalib(إلمطلب) was able to convince them by saying that he belongs to the most noble family in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
and he has to go back and learn about his heritage, and learn about his family, and start assuming responsibilities in Makkah.
Eventually, they agreed to allow him to go.
So, Al-Muttalib(إلمطلب) took with him this child into Makkah.
Now, nobody in Makkah has ever seen this child before.
And in those days, slavery was quite ramped,
you go out to the market and you buy a slave and you just walk in with that slave to Makkah.
Since this boy was never seen in Makkah before, they assumed, he is the slave of Al-Muttalib(اَلمطلب).
So, they called him Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب).
And this is the grandfather of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, his real name was Shaybah(شيبه),
but he was nicknamed Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب),
because they thought that, he's the slave of his uncle.
And usually they would buy slaves at a young age,
so that they would raise them up and train them to what you want them to do for you.
So, they would usually, purchase them when they're young.
So, they thought that he was a slave.
And he was named Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب), the slave of Al-Muttalib(المطلب),
Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) means the slave of Al-Muttalib(المطلب).
So, this is the grandfather of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, now we got for, as far as the grandfather of Rasool Allah.
We talked about Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) and Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل).
We talked about Qusae(قصئ).
And then we talked about Haashim(هاشم),
we've talks about Al-Muttalib(المطلب).
Now, we'll spend some time talking about Abdul-Muttalib(عبدالمطلب),
because a few important events happened to him.
Actually two, we'll talk about two important events that have occurred with Abdul-Muttalib(عبدالمطلب).
Remember that the well of Zam-Zam(زمزم) was now unknown, right?
Because Jurhum(جرهم), they erased all of its marks,
they filled it up and just erased all of its marks.
So, Zam-Zam(زمزم) has not been known now for about 300 years,
because Khuza'a(خزاعه) they had rule over Makkah for about 300 years.
And then you add to that, the time from Qusae Bin Kalaab(قصئ بن كلاب) all the way down to Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب),
so we're talking about 300 years plus.
So the well of Zam-Zam(زمزم) was lost for over 300 years.
Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) sees a dream.
Someone comes to him and tells him.
اُحْفُرْ طَيْبَهْ
Dig Tayba(طيبه).!
Tayba(طيبه) means pure.
Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) in his dream is responding and saying what is Tayba(طيبه)?
He doesn't hear anything back!
That was the end of the dream.
The following night,
the same voice comes to him and tells him.
اُحْفُرْ بَرَّهْ
Dig the precious.!
Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) says what is the precious?
He doesn't hear an answer back.
The third night,
the voice comes to him and tells him.
اُحْفُرْ زم زَمْ
Dig Zam-Zam(زمزم)!
Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) asked and what is Zam-Zam,?
The voice tells him.
زَم زَمْ لَا تَفْنَى وَلَا تَزَمْ تَسْقِي الْحَجِيْجَ الْأَعْظَمْ
بَيْنَ الْفَرْثِ وَالدَّمْ عِنْدَ قَرْيَةِ النَّمْلْ، عِنْدَ نَقْرَةْ اَلْغُرَابَ الْأعْصَمْ
The Voice tells him:
It will never fail or dry up,
it will water the grand pilgrim,
it lies between the dung and the blood,
near the nest of the crow, with the white leg and the ants nest.
So, it's symbols
and Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) is unable to decode all of these symbols.
زَم زَمْ لَا تَفْنَى وَلَا تَزَمْ
It never runs out of water.
He heard the voice, in his dream telling him that Zam-Zam(زمزم) will never run out of water,
تَسْقِي الْحَجِيْجَ الْأَعْظَمْ
And it will provide for the grand pilgrim, meaning Hajj(حَجْ) every year,
and it will be sufficient to provide water for them.
But then it goes into say,
بَيْنَ الْفَرْثِ وَالدَّمْ
Between Dung and blood.
And then crow with the white leg, nest of ants
and all of these are, obscure things to Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب).
Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) in the next day, he was going around the Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه),
and he sees Dung and Blood.
There was a camel that was slaughtered in that place,
and they left its insides and the blood was on the other side,
and then he saw a crow with the white leg in the same area,
and there was a colony of ants.
Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) realized that this is where the well of my grandfather is.!
So, he calls his son Al-Harris(الحارث) and they start digging.
Now, Zam-Zam(زمزم) for those of you, who have been to Makkah,
is not far away from Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
So, here you have Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) and his son digging, right next to Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
Obviously, this would anger the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
I mean, what are you doing, you're digging right next to Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
So, they told them what's, what are you doing.?
Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) continued working and they kept on protesting and he was digging with his son, Al-Harris(الحارث).
At the time Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) only had one son.
So, they were digging, and digging, and digging, and the people are wondering,
what's going on? What is this man digging for?
What is he looking for?
So, they left him alone.
And then suddenly, they heard Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) shout,
praising Allahسبحانه وتعالى,
and they came rushing.
And to their amazement, they found that Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) has uncovered the rim of the well of Zam-Zam(زمزم).
So, now all of the leaders of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), they came in, and said:
Yeah, this is the well of our grandfathers, Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل), this belongs to all of us.
Let's share, Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) said: wait, a minute,
I was the one, who saw the dream.
I was the one, who uncovered it.
It belongs to me, and me alone.
They said: No way.
We are all descendants of Ismailعليه السلام, so it belongs to all of us
Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) refused to give up,
he refused.
And they kept on insisting.
So, when they were unable to solve the dispute,
and they were about to go to war over it,
someone suggested to them,
let's solve the dispute by going to the witch of Banni Sa'ad(بني سعد).
Banni Sa'ad(بني سعد), they had a witch, who claimed to have connection with spirits.
So, let's go to her and seek her consultation.
So, they traveled to this witch.
And they were told that she has relocated and went to Syria.
So, they said, well, we'll follow her wherever she is.!
And they started their journey towards Ash-Sham(الشام).
And along the way, they ran out of water.
And they were in the middle of nowhere in the desert.
And Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) told them, if we going to die here.
Let's at least dig our graves.
And whenever one of us dies, the rest could put him, in the grave and cover him.
So, at least in the end, we will be left with one person, who's uncovered.
Rather than have all of us die, exposed,
at least let's honor our dead and just have one, that is without burial.
So, they all dug their graves,
and they were laying inside their graves waiting for death.
And then Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) he said, I mean, this is not right.
For men like us to sit here waiting for death.
Let's do something.
Let's go search for water.
So, they agreed and they went in different directions searching for water.
After a short while Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) found water.
So, they came to him, and said:
If Allah has saved you in this desert, and provided you with water,
and Allah has shown you a dream, in which you uncovered the well of Zam-Zam(زمزم).
This is surely an indication that's a blessing for you and it belongs to you.
We give up our claim, it's all yours.
Let's go back.
So, they gave it up and they agreed to submit to Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب), and it(زمزم) was his.
So, this is one important story that happened with Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب).
Now, when the whole incident happened, when they pressured him,
when they came to him and said this belongs to all of us,
Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) felt that he is weak because he has only one son to defend him,
you know, in the tribal societies,
your strength is based on how many men you have on your side,
and you can only count on your relatives.
That is how life in the desert is.
Your strength is based on how many sons
how many men you have with you, how many brothers, how many sons,
how many uncles that is your strength.
So, Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) felt weak, he has only one son, on his side, Al-Harris(الحارث).
So, he said, O Allah, if you bestow me with 10 sons,
I will sacrifice one of them for Your sake.
And Allahسبحانه وتعالى did bless him with 10 male sons.
He had 10 male sons and six daughters.
So, when he had 10.
Now, it's time for him to fulfill his promise to Allah, that he will sacrifice one of them.
So, they had these arrows next to Hubal(حبل),
Hubal(حبل) is, one of their large idols.
And they believe that these arrows were divine, so they would cast lots
and they would leave their choices, they would leave the decision up to the this random way of casting lots.
So, Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) had the name of every one of his 10 sons on these arrows.
So, it came one who.?
Abdullah(عبدالله),
he did it a second time it came on Abdullah(عبدالله), third time it came on Abdullah(عبدالله).
So, Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) took his son Abdullah(عبدالله) with him,
right next to the Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) and he was ready with a knife to slaughter him.
Abu Talib(ابوطالب), one of the elder sons of Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) went to his father and said,
We cannot allow you to kill your son.
And then the maternal relatives of Abdullah(عبدالله) came and said,
we're not going to allow you to kill our son.
And people were coming in and they were telling Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب),
if you do it, then it will become Sunnah(سنة) for the Arabs after you.
Because Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) was their leader.
So, if he did something, it would become a trend after that.
And they said, if you do it,
then any one of us, after that to us 10 sons will follow your footsteps.
And we will be killing each other.
I mean, they were already killing their daughters, and now they will start killing their sons.
So, they insisted on Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) not to do it.
Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) told them this was a pledge that I did to Allah.
I cannot give it up, I cannot break my promise.
They told him, No, you have to stop it.
Anyway, they had to dispute.
How can they solve this dispute?
Let's go to the witch.
So, they decided to go and visit the witch again.
They went to the witch and they told her,
this is the situation.
She said, All right, come back to me tomorrow, so that I can consult my spirits, this evening.
Tonight, I'll speak to the Jinn.
They came back the next day and she had an answer for them.
She told them.
What is the retribution that you pay, to a person that was killed?,
Diya(دية),
the blood money, how much is it?
They said 10 camels.
She said then put 10 camels on one side
and put Abdullah(عبدالله) on the other side and cast a lot.
If it points towards the camels, then slaughter the camels,
if it points towards Abdullah(عبدالله), then add another 10 camels.
So, they agreed and they went back,
so Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) with all of the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), they came together,
Abdullah(عبدالله) on one side, the camels on the other side, they threw the dice or the arrows
it pointed towards Abdullah(عبدالله).
They added another 10 camels.
It's pointed towards Abdullah(عبدالله),
added another 10.
So, now we're up to 30, 40, 50, 60,
and it's pointing towards Abdullah(عبدالله) all the way, until a 100.
They had 100 camels on one side Abdullah(عبدالله) on the other side, finally it pointed towards the camels.
The people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) said:
Finally, we can release your son Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) said not yet.
We'll have to do it another time.
Cast lots the second time, cast lot the third time,
it was consistently pointing towards the camels.
So, he slaughtered the hundred camels and he had to pay for it all.
And Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) was a very generous man, he refused to take any of that meat,
he gave it out and there was so much meat,
that there was so much and the people would, take so much of it,
but there was still enough to feed the birds and to feed the beasts.
So later on, they would say: Ya'ani(يعني)
it became famous among the Arabs that Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) is the one, who fed the humans and the animals.
مطعم اَطَّيْرْ فِيْ السَّمَاء
He's the one who even fed the birds in the sky.
And we'll talk about an incident when this saying was brought up,
in a conversation with Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) and one leader of a clan.
Now, the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) were right,
when they told Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) if you kill your son,
it will become a tradition among the Arabs after you,
because when Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب) sacrificed a 100 camels to save his son,
the blood money among them changed from 10 camels to 100,
because of what happened with Abdul Muttalib(عبد المطلب).
So, the retribution now that is paid was 100 rather than 10.
And by the way, this tradition was kept and reserved by Islam.
So, the Diya(ديعا) is still today 100 camels,
however now, they would calculate it in terms of currency,
but it is still based on that concept.
This is the story of Abdullah(عبدالله).
Now, Abdullah(عبدالله) and Aamna(آمنه) are the parents of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Later on, they would tell Muhammadﷺ that you are the son of the two sacrificed ones.
And who are they.?
Who are the two sacrifice one's.?
Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) and Abdullah(عبدالله).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is the son of the two sacrifice ones,
his father Abdullah(عبدالله) was sacrificed and his father Ismail عليه السلام was sacrificed.
Abdullah(عبدالله) married Aamna Bint Wahb(آمنه بنت وهب).
And we're done with the ancestry of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًاكَثِيْرَا